<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects | Fons Research Group</title>
    <link>/project/</link>
      <atom:link href="/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Projects</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>P. Fons ©</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 27 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>/project/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Machine Learning/Materials Informatics</title>
      <link>/project/machinelearning/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/machinelearning/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the caveats of density-functional theory is that calculations can produce copious amounts of output. Due to the
complexity and volume of the output, this can lead to challenges in interpreting the generated output. Here well
use CEGANN: Crystal Edge Graph Attention Neural Network for multiscale classification of materials environment[1] In this example,
we represent bonds between atoms as well as bond angle information in a mathematical graph in an attention based architecture.
These graphs are then introduced as an input layer to a convolutional neural network to &amp;ldquo;learn&amp;rdquo; the local environment
about atoms in the three-dimensional structure. By training on amorphous and crystalline structures generated using &lt;em&gt;ab-initio&lt;/em&gt;*
molecular dynamics, the nature of a site in a three-dimensional network can be distinguished as being crystalline or
amorphous in nature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1] S. Banik, D. Dhabal, H. Chan, S. Manna, M. Cherukara, V. Molinero, and S. K. R. S. Sankaranarayanan. Cegann: Crystal edge graph attention neural network for multiscale classification of materials environ- ment. npj Computational Materials, 9(1):23, 2023.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Density-Functional Theory</title>
      <link>/project/dft/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/dft/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Density-functional theory (DFT) is used to predict a variety of material properties. In addition,
ab-initio molecular dynamics based upon DFT is used to examine structural dynamics and
to generate metastable (amorphous phases) by means of a melt-quench process. The plane-wave codes
VASP (Vienna Ab initio Simulation Package), CASTEP (CAmbridge Serial Total Energy Package),
as well as the FP-(L)APW+lo code Wien2K are used to investigate both structural and electronic
properties of samples under study. In addition the real-space Greens function code Feff9 and
FMDNES codes are used for the simulation of x-ray absorption data. The figure above shows the charge-density difference (CDD)
for a cross-section of the GeTe lattice which has both short and long bonds. The CDD plot is constructed
by taking the difference between the charge density of the solid and pseudo-atoms. As such the pileup
of charge between two atoms is suggestive of a covalent bond as describe by Pauling.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ultrafast Dynamics</title>
      <link>/project/ultrafast/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/ultrafast/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Ultrafast measurements of chemical reactions and phonon behavior have been carried out using
time-resolve synchrotron radiation-based x-ray absorption, free-electron laser diffraction,
as well as all-optical pump-probe experiments. Above is a plot of the time-dependence of
a free-electron based optical-pump/ x-ray probe diffraction experiment on a Ge₂Sb₂Te₅ single epilayer (left) along with
a simulation of the diffraction signal based upon the propagation of the acoustic phonon generated
by the 20 fs optical pump pulse.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Phase-Change Materials</title>
      <link>/project/pcm/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/pcm/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The idea of using structure for storage dates back to the 1960&amp;rsquo;s with the seminal work of Stanford
Ovshinsky who proposed a four component chalcogenide alloy as a form of nonvolatile
electrical memory. The higher power requirements of the phase-change memory (PCM)
limited its application until the 1980&amp;rsquo;s when the pioneering work at Matsushita lead to
the development of Ge-Sb-Te PCM alloys and its application to re-writeable optical discs.
This has now lead to optical disc storage capacities to exceed 50 GB. Moreover, the same
Ge-Sb-Te alloys are now employed in the form of storage-class memory (as epitomized by Intel&amp;rsquo;s
Optane memory subsystems), a form of nonvolatile
electrical memory with latencies and write times within a factor of 10 of DRAM alleviating the
bottlenecks associated with the larger latency of the denser nonvolatile FLASH memory. Even
more recently a new variation of electrical memory called interfacial phase-change memory
(iPCM) has appeared which uses highly oriented superlattices of GeTe and Sb2Te3 to achieve more
than a factor of ten reduction in energy requirements by use of what is thought to be a crystalline-crystalline
transition. The figure above represents a possible atomic level model for the switching process
in iPCM devices.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Structure of Amorphous Materials</title>
      <link>/project/amorphous_materials/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/amorphous_materials/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The structure and properties of amorphous materials have been traditionally hard to analyze
as one of the most ubiquitous tools for structural analysis x-ray (Bragg) diffraction is not
applicable. On the other hand, the material properties of the amorphous phase have proven to be
very useful for applications. A case in point is phase-change memory which utilizes the properties
differences between crystalline and amorphous phases for data storage. Our group specializes
in using a combination of synchrotron based techniques such as x-ray absorption spectroscopy,
high-energy photoelectron spectroscopy, as well as total scattering to experimentally determine the local
structure of amorphous materials. These experimental results in conjunction with density-functional
theory-based analysis and ab-initio molecular dynamics has allowed the unraveling of the
unique properties of different phase-change alloys.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
