<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>DFT | Fons Research Group</title>
    <link>/tag/dft/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tag/dft/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>DFT</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>P. Fons ©</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 27 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>DFT</title>
      <link>/tag/dft/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Machine Learning/Materials Informatics</title>
      <link>/project/machinelearning/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/machinelearning/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the caveats of density-functional theory is that calculations can produce copious amounts of output. Due to the
complexity and volume of the output, this can lead to challenges in interpreting the generated output. Here well
use CEGANN: Crystal Edge Graph Attention Neural Network for multiscale classification of materials environment[1] In this example,
we represent bonds between atoms as well as bond angle information in a mathematical graph in an attention based architecture.
These graphs are then introduced as an input layer to a convolutional neural network to &amp;ldquo;learn&amp;rdquo; the local environment
about atoms in the three-dimensional structure. By training on amorphous and crystalline structures generated using &lt;em&gt;ab-initio&lt;/em&gt;*
molecular dynamics, the nature of a site in a three-dimensional network can be distinguished as being crystalline or
amorphous in nature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1] S. Banik, D. Dhabal, H. Chan, S. Manna, M. Cherukara, V. Molinero, and S. K. R. S. Sankaranarayanan. Cegann: Crystal edge graph attention neural network for multiscale classification of materials environ- ment. npj Computational Materials, 9(1):23, 2023.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Role of Electric fields in interfacial phase-change memory</title>
      <link>/publication/e-fields/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/e-fields/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!-- 
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Click the &lt;em&gt;Slides&lt;/em&gt; button above to demo Academic&amp;rsquo;s Markdown slides feature.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

 --&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Density-Functional Theory</title>
      <link>/project/dft/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/dft/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Density-functional theory (DFT) is used to predict a variety of material properties. In addition,
ab-initio molecular dynamics based upon DFT is used to examine structural dynamics and
to generate metastable (amorphous phases) by means of a melt-quench process. The plane-wave codes
VASP (Vienna Ab initio Simulation Package), CASTEP (CAmbridge Serial Total Energy Package),
as well as the FP-(L)APW+lo code Wien2K are used to investigate both structural and electronic
properties of samples under study. In addition the real-space Greens function code Feff9 and
FMDNES codes are used for the simulation of x-ray absorption data. The figure above shows the charge-density difference (CDD)
for a cross-section of the GeTe lattice which has both short and long bonds. The CDD plot is constructed
by taking the difference between the charge density of the solid and pseudo-atoms. As such the pileup
of charge between two atoms is suggestive of a covalent bond as describe by Pauling.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
